

📕 (+1) 707-529-8516 | 🗷 wconnell93@gmail.com | 💣 wconnell.github.io | 🖸 wconnell | 🛅 will-connell-26412352 | 💆 @wilstc

RESEARCH SCIENTIST, MACHINE LEARNING THIS.

Summary_

At Vevo Therapeutics, I led machine learning initiatives from seed funding, establishing the technical foundations for a scRNA-seq drug discovery platform. My graduate research in sequence-based representation learning informed our strategy, leveraging my experience in integrating chemical and omic features to predict and understand drug responses. I enjoy working in collaborative environments and communicating industry developments to the broader community.

Education

University of California, San Francisco

San Francisco, CA

PhD in Pharmaceutical Sciences and Pharmacogenomics

BS IN MICROBIOLOGY, IMMUNOLOGY AND MOLECULAR GENETICS

2018 - 2022

· Advisor: Michael Keiser

· Committee: Hani Goodarzi, Luke Gilbert

University of California, Los Angeles

Los Angeles, CA

2012 - 2016

Experience ___

Vevo Therapeutics San Francisco, CA

RESEARCH SCIENTIST, MACHINE LEARNING

September 2022 - January 2024

- Developed and executed strategy for a scRNA-seq foundation model (scFM), expanding the pretraining corpus 65x and significantly improving target retrieval, sensitivity prediction, and biological recapitulation tasks
- Conceived and delivered a multimodal model aligning transcriptomes and chemical structures, achieving a 10x increase in top-k accuracy
- · Initiated the ML strategy for chemical graph generation using transcriptional profiles for phenotype-guided small molecule design
- · Led a proposal accepted into the AWS Gen AI Accelerator program (<1%), securing \$300k compute credits and industry recognition
- Managed contractors, recruited three FTEs, and mentored an intern, growing the ML team by 50%

Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry, UCSF

San Francisco, CA

GRADUATE RESEARCHER ADVISED BY MICHAEL KEISER

March 2019 - December 2022

- Pioneered the application of self-supervised learning to scRNA-seq, advancing the pretrain/finetune framework in biological modeling
- Developed an in silico model for chemical probing (+10% baseline), finding new indication responses and potential ferroptosis drug targets
- · Identified a genomic biomarker to stratify mAb ustekinumab response in psoriasis, advancing personalized treatment decisions

Al Research Group, Invitae

Remote

COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY RESEARCH INTERN

May 2021 - August 2021

- · Aided in developing a hierarchical Bayesian model to enhance polygenic risk scoring accuracy
- · Involved in comprehensive software and pipeline engineering for efficient management and analysis of large-scale datasets

UCSF Innovation Ventures

San Francisco, CA

CATALYST AWARDS INTERN

PROJECT DEVELOPER

September 2018 - September 2019

- · Assessed scientific translation potential of a diagnostic gene expression biomarker panel, collaborating with corporate strategy experts
- · Headed a team of four scientists to develop a Target Product Profile, resulting in a \$100k translational funding award
- Performed product development feasibility studies, yielding a comprehensive report and pitch to venture investors

Datacamp Remote

• Crafted and delivered a data science project for a premier online educational platform

November 2019 - January 2019

- Craited and delivered a data science project for a premier online educational platform
- Developed an interactive data analysis course in R, Data Science for Social Good: Crime Study
- Successfully engaged over 2000 learners, achieving a course rating of 4.7/5

Publications

JOURNAL ARTICLES

Learning chemical sensitivity reveals mechanisms of cellular response

William Connell, Kristle Garcia, Hani Goodarzi, Michael J Keiser

Commun. Biol. 7.1 (Sept. 2024) p. 1149. Springer, 2024. DOI: 10.1038/s42003-024-06865-4

DNA-Diffusion: Leveraging Generative Models for Controlling Chromatin Accessibility and Gene Expression via Synthetic Regulatory Elements

Lucas Ferreira DaSilva, Simon Senan, Zain Munir Patel, Aniketh Janardhan Reddy, Sameer Gabbita, Zach Nussbaum, Cesar Miguel Valdez Cordova, Aaron Wenteler, Noah Weber, Tin M. Tunjic, Talha Ahmad Khan, Zelun Li, Cameron Ray Smith, Matei Bejan, Lithin Karmel Louis, Paola Cornejo, William Connell, Emily S. Wong, Wouter Meuleman, Luca Pinello

bioRxiv (2024). Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, 2024. DOI: 10.1101/2024.02.01.578352

Genome-wide association study of ustekinumab response in psoriasis

William Connell, Julie Hong, Wilson Liao

Frontiers in Immunology 12 (Jan. 2022). 2022. DOI: 10.3389/fimmu.2021.815121

A single-cell gene expression language model

William Connell, Umair Khan, Michael J. Keiser

LMRL Workshop, NeurIPS (Oct. 2022). 2022. DOI: 10.48550/arXiv.2210.14330

Predicting cellular drug sensitivity using conditional modulation of gene expression

William Connell, Michael J. Keiser

LMRL Workshop, NeurIPS (Dec. 2020). 2020. DOI: 10.1101/2021.03.15.435529

Helical antimicrobial peptides assemble into protofibril scaffolds that present ordered dsDNA to TLR9

Ernest Y. Lee, Changsheng Zhang, Jeremy Di Domizio, Fan Jin, William Connell, Mandy Hung, Nicolas Malkoff, Veronica Veksler, Michel Gilliet, Pengyu Ren, Gerard C.L. Wong

Nat. Commun. 10.1 (Mar. 2019) p. 1012. 2019. DOI: 10.1038/s41467-019-08868-w

A single-cell transcriptomic atlas of human neocortical development during mid-gestation

Damon Polioudakis, Luis Torre-Ubieta, Justin Langerman, Andrew G. Elkins, Xu Shi, Jason L. Stein, Celine K. Vuong, Susanne Nichterwitz, Melinda Gevorgian, Carli K. Opland, Daning Lu, William Connell, Elizabeth K. Ruzzo, Jennifer K. Lowe, Tarik Hadzic, Flora I. Hinz, Shan Sabri, William E. Lowry, Mark B. Gerstein, Kathrin Plath, Daniel H. Geschwind

Neuron 103.5 (Sept. 2019) 785-801.e8. 2019. DOI: 10.1016/j.neuron.2019.06.011

PRESENTATIONS

Quantifying the similarity of transcriptomic states in cancer

William Connell, Michael J. Keiser

CZI Neurodegeneration Challenge Network 2020 Annual Meeting. Poster. 2020. Virtual.

Target deconvolution across phenotypic space

William Connell, Garrett Gaskins, Michael J. Keiser

Northern California Computational Biology Symposium. Oral. 2019. Davis, CA.

Extracurricular Activity

Behind BioML Remote

SUBSTACK, WRITING Current

- · Scaling biology: genomics
- · Picks & shovels of the AI bioeconomy
- · An emerging business model in drug development
- Scaling biology: transcriptomics
- · Computation through the lens of biology
- ML for target identification
- The evolution of ML in early-stage drug development

SynBioBeta San Jose, CA

FOUNDATION MODELS FOR BIO PANEL · Moderator for panel discussion: technical overview, role of data, model evals, and impact on industry verticals

ICLR Remote

MLGenX Workshop Reviewer 2024

Machine Learning for Genomics Explorations workshop (reviewer)

OpenBioML Remote

DNA DIFFUSION, CONTRIBUTING MEMBER

August 2023 - Present

2024

- Contributed to OS research focusing on in silico generative sequence design
- Led the creation of an oracle model for assessing DNA sequences, improving baseline model 18x
- Coordinated scientific and technical efforts among a diverse group of global collaborators

Skills

python [numpy, pandas, pytorch, scikit-learn, huggingface, wandb, lightning, pytorch-geometric, rdkit, hydra], programming

AWS, R, bash, git, plink, snakemake

OS contributions enformer-finetune, pytorch-metric-learning, scikit-learn sprint (WiMLDS)

model repos ChemProbe, Exceiver